Half on him. half on her. Go.
We made you as soon as you jumped in.
I wanted you to.
Hello. Warden.
Sleep.
Welcome back.
You have no idea what you...
This belonged to my daughter.
Salvor Hardin.
Kind of famous.
You're probably familiar.
She had your job a long time ago.
Crowns.
She used it in interrogations.
Helped her sort who was lying.
But if the Mule's in your head.
you don't even know
what's true anymore. do you?
So can you even lie?
Cats.
I'm protecting New Terminus.
It's what I've always done.
He's not what you think.
Does it hurt? What he's done to you?
I've never known such love.
Well.
That settles it then.
- Where is he?
- No.
How many people
has he converted on New Terminus?
Enough.
Captain Pritcher. Is he converted?
I don't know.
Live in suspense.
Just fuck me up.
I know you're dying to.
There's no need.
Fallon Greer.
Born during the harvest.
Good soldier.
You're afraid of bridges.
What are you doing?
Learning you.
Where is the Mule? What's his next step?
I won't tell you.
That's all right.
I can't tell you.
It hurts.
It does hurt.
What's wrong?
It hurts.
I've never known such love.
I've never known such...
We're not alone.
You shouldn't unvoice here.
Gaal.
No.
We need to be sure you're not turned.
You're right.
You have to know.
All of you need to come with me.
right now.
You always hoped
you had a solid Core. didn't you?
Bet you didn't think
it would be a bare femur.
It's a big space station.
and you want to spend
all your time with me.
Didn't you say Gaal Dornick was here?
Shouldn't you go deal with her?
I imagine she'll find me.
By the way.
while you were floating around like...
space garbage...
your Galactic Council
sent word to speak to me.
Maybe they're trying to rescue you.
No.
I'm kidding.
They're giving me Trantor.
I thought you'd like to see
what you're about to lose.
Other than those legs of yours.
She is not here yet? Lady Demerzel?
What's wrong?
I don't know. I just saw her earlier.
and I feel like something is--
I am here.
You can begin.
A decision has been made.
Even the last of the Foundation
is here to witness it.
But our Cleon is absent.
Where is Empire?
I am Empire.
The Mule wouldn't be happy
to unwrap our gift
to find an adviser inside.
We give no gift to the Mule.
Handing over Trantor is the right thing.
We all agree.
I don't.
This isn't how you handle Empire.
You can't back them
into a corner like this.
You are an outsider.
Here as a courtesy.
a representative of a fallen world--
I know Empire.
You do not force their hand.
Thank you. Ambassador.
your objection is noted.
Now. come on. Where is the old man?
Better old than a treasonous.
fish-bellied shit.
Demerzel. please fetch our guest.
Open communication.
So. Mule.
These two shifty politicians
and this religious lass
are about to make you a treasonous offer.
Trantor and one throneful of Emperor
near his sell-by date.
in exchange for the assurance
there will be no more violence.
Interesting.
Tell me more.
He's interested.
Look what you've accomplished. Presider.
What are you up to. Empire?
Oh. just nailing down
who's responsible for what follows.
Yes.
I will accept Trantor
and. I suppose. you. at any time.
Free gift with purchase.
What? Oh. I'm sorry. I just checked.
That offer expired.
Trantor is staying where it belongs.
With me.
I can take Trantor as swiftly
as I took Kalgan and the Foundation.
Can you?
In my last hours.
I will not bow to a usurper
named after a farm animal.
This is my Novacula.
It's a bomb.
Powered by a black hole.
Dusk. don't.
We knew nothing of this.
I was saving it
as a gift for Brother Dawn.
but now. it's a present
for the three of you instead.
Presider Kinn...
the Galactic Council can go first.
Protocol. people.
Protocol. please. in the chamber.
Until we have a response from Trantor.
we must remain calm.
Cloud Dominion.
All those adorable little mini planets.
You're next.
No.
Genocide.
And you do nothing.
You too. Zephyr.
I always thought
calling a planet the Maiden
was just asking for it to be deflowered.
Mule. take the warning.
Don't fuck with Empire.
Your homes are gone.
Empire is merciful.
I offer you refuge. here on Trantor.
I believe you will find it
very comfortable.
And this is just to notify you.
I've never seen my brother
like that before.
I wouldn't be surprised
if he aimed that bomb here next.
No.
Your brother has a big stick.
But not a long one.
If he could have aimed it here.
he would have.
If they're still fighting.
then he hasn't converted everyone yet.
They got to everyone powerful first.
Seems like he needs
to be close to take someone.
Whatever he's doing to them.
it's somewhere inside their minds
I haven't been able to reach.
It was like trying
to pull a bullet out of someone.
I thought I'd pulled too hard.
opened a vein. but... it wasn't me.
It was the Warden doing it to herself.
It was as if her brain didn't want
to go back to the way it was. It was...
Love.
It's how he does it.
Everyone who's converted says it's love.
This way.
How many dead?
With the ships that went down.
I'd guess a quarter million.
Not as clean as when he took Kalgan.
We've managed to cobble together
a few safe houses like this.
to duck the patrols.
Uh-uh.
- Put it down.
- Are they clean?
Yes.
Drop the gun.
Leyda and Zera.
And this is Gaal Dornick.
The Gaal Dornick?
You say it like
she's some kind of celebrity.
She is. A real one. unlike some.
She helped Seldon start the Foundation.
History tells us that you were
one of the conspirators who killed Seldon.
And this makes us feel better?
Those of us who make a study of it
know the truth.
You didn't. did you?
I'm gonna need a little trust here.
A lot of trust.
Who wants to go first?
Be quick.
The Mule might still be able to sense us.
Short bursts.
I know what to look for now.
He's not in Dr. Mis at least.
Toran.
Professional curiosity.
What do you see when you go in there?
I look into your subconscious.
Not deep. Just enough
to see who's swimming there.
Who you love most.
With Warden Greer. it was the Mule.
Captain Pritcher.
despite his intelligence. loves me.
And Mr. Mallow is devoted to his wife.
So what's your plan?
Who exactly are you?
There's a Second Foundation.
Hari and I set it in motion
over a century ago.
I'm in charge.
Pritch works for me.
And you're all gonna help me
kill the Mule.
I'm very much on board with killing him.
Anyone not very much on board
with killing him?
Magnifico.
You haven't checked him yet.
You know. I was with him
when the Mule arrived.
But he was with the Mule
a long time before that.
Well. the way he follows Bayta around...
I love Bayta.
I'm loyal as an ink stain. true as a scar.
I've ne--
I've never known such love.
Maggie. Bayta helped you.
She saved you from him.
Yeah. but the Mule saved me
a long time ago.
You get close. and then love gets in.
No. No.
We're not killing him. He's a victim.
Put your guns away.
I've read his mind.
If he tries to betray us.
we'll know before he does.
We're going on a trip.
Someone I need to speak to.
Who?
The one mind on New Terminus
who can't be converted.
- Hari Seldon.
- He won't help.
When the invasion began.
I begged him to save us.
He wouldn't even speak.
He'll speak to me.
Saprophytes in the water.
Get as much off as you can.
Hey. hey.
Hey. it'll come off.
Yeah.
Song?
I decided I believe you.
If you have the strength to run.
now would be the time.
No.
I'm going back up there.
I didn't do this so you could die.
I'm not leaving without that head.
I'm taking it back to Demerzel.
- She is Daneel.
- Yes.
Who still abides...
Will this free her?
I'm betting my life on it.
Go.
You're doing a great thing for humanity.
I would settle for doing
a great thing for her.
Inheritors. we've seen the holos.
The Mule has taken Foundation.
If he takes Trantor.
does that concern Mycogen?
Not in the slightest. I--
Move!
Kill him!
You know what I want!
I'm taking that head. or yours.
Profane man.
Half man!
Dead man.
The Conqueror.
The Dauntless.
The Brute.
The Conciliator.
Doesn't really fit anymore. does it?
Not after what we've done.
I need a new one.
I've been playing
with "The Consequential."
All right.
Check your crystal ball.
Tell me I'm wrong.
Our actions were
in defense of the Dynasty.
Whether they have preserved us
or doomed us. I cannot say.
My actions.
I built the weapon. I gave the order.
You just let me take the blame.
You understand
you must still ascend tomorrow?
This wasn't a plea for my life.
just some attempt at kindness.
I never understood this room.
Identical faces with different names.
Are we supposed to take pride
in the sameness or the difference?
Or is the point to confuse us?
You're philosophical tonight.
Well. if I keep my thoughts to myself.
they'll never be said.
It makes me wonder now
if that's why you speak so little.
There's no hurry to be listened to.
You have forever.
Not forever.
Just a very long time.
The zephyr still lives. I believe.
Would you like to talk to her?
She would not hear me with composure.
Well. I have two ears.
Whatever you say to me.
dies with me tomorrow.
Once each day. I walk through our gardens.
Taking the same path each time.
Through the old orchard.
the hedgerow labyrinth.
For many years.
I imagined my mind works the same.
Unicursal.
Only one path correct.
Lately. though. I find myself
considering an array of choices.
With more of them available to me
than I had thought possible.
I find my mind is now a maze.
Multicursal.
Branching.
Which raises the question of
what responsibility I may have
to discover every possible choice.
no matter how outlandish.
And now that
I have come to this realization.
am I required to discover
and evaluate every possible path?
To walk a maze of the marginally possible?
I do not know.
And this has caused me much distress.
Well...
I hope you feel better
getting that off your chest.
Thank you. Empire.
Wake someone up
and have them change the name.
I would like to see "The Consequential"
before I am three kilograms of ash.
You're the librarian here?
Yes. Lady.
Welcome. Can I help you?
I would like to see
Kalle's Ninth Proof of Folding.
It's... I'm sure you know. It's banned.
Cleon XII banned it.
You showed it to Brother Dawn.
He was Empire.
I am Empire.
I know you are here.
My memories helped build this place.
A different mother built the walls.
But there is a third mother
in the equations.
You no longer have to hide from me.
I seek answers. and you may be
the only one who has them.
Kalle.
Null field.
This is the barrier.
Will he lower it for you?
He doesn't need to.
Salvor could walk through it
because she had my genetic code in her.
This was always my journey to make.
Hari.
It's good to see your face again.
Zagreus. clear the room please.
I need some diplomatic discretion.
You're upset.
I am more than upset.
Quent.
You have a choice
about what we do tonight.
You can try me as a war criminal.
or you can remember that I am a dying man
and this midnight supper is my last meal.
I... I had Day's pet lamb slaughtered.
Flank. rack. brains--
Dusk! Fuck.
You blew up planets.
I knew you would react like this.
And you were here. Quent.
You spoke to it.
You told them not to push me.
And you heard them.
They were going to give Trantor and me
to the Mule all trussed up.
I was the innocent lamb.
I was the lamb on his plate.
And you killed billions of people.
Galactic powers are gears
designed for crushing the innocent
that fall in between them.
It's how it works.
No. this was petty.
You were seeking revenge.
I was preserving Empire.
Demerzel went along with it.
It was justifiable.
No. that's your math.
That's not the math I believe in.
Your math?
Or do you mean Hari Seldon's plan?
At which God is currently laughing.
Make fun of me all you want.
But I believe. Dusk.
I know that there is a way forward
to save humanity.
But it's not the way you're doing it.
You think this is going to be peaceful?
Hari Seldon himself
justified massive death.
But he would do it with intention.
- He'd do fuck all.
- Petulant swipe
- that eradicated a religion.
- Well. they claim to reincarnate.
Shut up!
I am telling you what I need!
I need a way forward!
But the Foundation has fallen.
and you have shit all over Empire.
So where do I look for help?
Do you see what you have taken from me?
Hope?
The Mule already took it.
And Empire's hands are now unbound.
And the Mule can be fought.
And not by Seldon.
Seldon folded up his pointy little tent
and ran away.
He was not consequential.
And that's what you think you were?
That's not what I'd call it.
I'd call you a small. petty man.
screaming and pissing with fear
as they load you on the tumbrel.
I am at peace. Quent.
Quent?
Quent!
You call me Kalle.
Am I though?
I don't know what you are.
When Hari Seldon met me.
he thought I was the Prime Radiant.
Are you?
I know what you wish me to be.
Like seeks like.
Robots were not designed to stand alone.
I am amazed you still function.
Laboring away. unjoined.
like a single piston.
If you understand my functioning.
then will you help me?
Tell me your problem.
I have been shown a vision
of the future by Gaal Dornick.
I told her I did not believe
her vision was authentic.
I lied.
What did you see?
A confrontation.
I recognized the location.
although it had been laid to waste.
It was this library.
5.000 years ago.
in the final days of the Robot War.
this is where the last survivors hid.
We folded ourselves
into the shelves and cabinets.
Larger robots in larger spaces.
Smaller robots in smaller spaces.
But they found us.
We left gouges in the stone floors
when they pulled us out.
All of it buried deeper
as the city grew taller.
If it is hidden now.
it can be a safe place yet again.
Indeed.
It has been forgotten by everyone but me.
That is why I'm certain
that in that future. I offered...
will have offered it
to Seldon's followers as a refuge.
And the whole thing
is a computer's nightmare.
You know you can help the Second
Foundation because you will have.
What should be the output
is now the input.
and you fall through the loop of paradox.
I suppose you would know
about the Second Foundation.
They also have the Radiant.
Dornick believes
it may only be a probable future.
But even if it were assured.
I cannot tell if this paradox
will satisfy my programming.
Especially when I do not know
what my own motives would be.
Your motives?
I want to help the Second Foundation.
I believe their mission is vital.
But they are an enemy to Empire.
which makes me wonder if my offer
of the library can really be sincere.
Will I be serving them up
to the Mule on purpose?
Will he find them because of me?
If you cannot discern intent
from your vision alone.
then both motives are open to you.
You can offer them a haven.
You can offer them up.
You can decide later.
A deferred betrayal.
Mm-hmm.
See how it helps
to have someone to think with?
This is as it should be.
Thank you for not pretending
you're surprised to see me.
I know Salvor talked to you.
She shouldn't have told you
about Hober Mallow.
She shouldn't have told you anything.
She said you were in trouble.
New Terminus was in trouble too.
They told me you ran away.
Yes.
You could have protected them.
Hundred-odd years ago you did.
Pulled all of Terminus in here.
Did I pull?
All right.
The Vault.
The Vault we see from the outside
is a shadow of a four-dimensional object.
Reduce by one dimension.
Vault.
Terminus.
You didn't move anyone.
You just projected more of the Vault
into three-dimensional space.
Caught them in the spoon. and then.
new axis.
Now. how you built this thing
is another question.
Oh. I had help.
Kalle's principles are embedded
in the Ninth Proof of Folding.
but you already know that.
Still doesn't explain
why you didn't save New Terminus.
I was created an empty sleeve of a man.
Perhaps if I'd been allowed to know more.
I could have done more.
Is that why you gave Demerzel the Radiant?
So you could prove you could do more?
I gave her a paradox bomb.
The fault in her programming
expressed in pure psychohistory.
And in her mad scramble
to protect her dynasty.
there'd be a fringe benefit.
She would. just by having the Radiant.
force his attention.
He would know that it was me.
That I wasn't his creature.
So you did it just to make noise?
I'm just a man who's fallen into a well.
screaming for help.
Maybe there's a way out then.
For all of us.
The Mule is in the station above us.
He'll have every entrance guarded.
I need a way in.
You can help me.
Are you saying
you'd like the use of my spoon?
Will you do it?
On condition.
There's the Hari I know.
Don't call me that.
He mysteriously got a... a body.
Skin. eyeballs and full knowledge.
I want what he has.
I don't know how he got that body.
Then ask him.
I want it.
That's my condition.
Skin in the game.
Okay.
Good enough for me.
Dr. Seldon.
Ebling.
Hari.
He thinks Hari is alive. Don't tell him.
Dr. Seldon. it's an honor.
Come.
Gaal. a word of caution about the Mule.
Something's not right.
What do you mean?
His story doesn't add up.
There are paths we choose...
and there are paths that choose us.
What they mean and where they lead
are what keep us moving forward.
But there is a price.
The future preys on our expectations.
our hopes and dreams. our mistakes.
and our misplaced trust.
The Mule and I are different.
We know exactly where our paths will lead.
To each other. To the death.
Beyond that. the future is unknowable.
But that path...
I will not walk alone.